<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bible translation="English NIV">
  <testament name="New">
    <book name="John">
      <chapter number="12">
        <verse number="1">Six days before the Passover, Jesus arrived at Bethany, where Lazarus lived, whom Jesus had raised from the dead.</verse>
        <verse number="2">Here a dinner was given in Jesus' honor. Martha served, while Lazarus was among those reclining at the table with him.</verse>
        <verse number="3">Then Mary took about a pint of pure nard, an expensive perfume; she poured it on Jesus' feet and wiped his feet with her hair. And the house was filled with the fragrance of the perfume.</verse>
        <verse number="4">But one of his disciples, Judas Iscariot, who was later to betray him, objected,</verse>
        <verse number="5">"Why wasn't this perfume sold and the money given to the poor? It was worth a year's wages. "</verse>
        <verse number="6">He did not say this because he cared about the poor but because he was a thief; as keeper of the money bag, he used to help himself to what was put into it.</verse>
        <verse number="7">"Leave her alone," Jesus replied. "It was intended that she should save this perfume for the day of my burial.</verse>
        <verse number="8">You will always have the poor among you, but you will not always have me."</verse>
        <verse number="9">Meanwhile a large crowd of Jews found out that Jesus was there and came, not only because of him but also to see Lazarus, whom he had raised from the dead.</verse>
        <verse number="10">So the chief priests made plans to kill Lazarus as well,</verse>
        <verse number="11">for on account of him many of the Jews were going over to Jesus and putting their faith in him.</verse>
        <verse number="12">The next day the great crowd that had come for the Feast heard that Jesus was on his way to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse number="13">They took palm branches and went out to meet him, shouting, "Hosanna! Blessed is he who comes in the name of the Lord!Blessed is the King of Israel!"</verse>
        <verse number="14">Jesus found a young donkey and sat upon it, as it is written,</verse>
        <verse number="15">"Do not be afraid, O Daughter of Zion; see, your king is coming, seated on a donkey's colt."</verse>
        <verse number="16">At first his disciples did not understand all this. Only after Jesus was glorified did they realize that these things had been written about him and that they had done these things to him.</verse>
        <verse number="17">Now the crowd that was with him when he called Lazarus from the tomb and raised him from the dead continued to spread the word.</verse>
        <verse number="18">Many people, because they had heard that he had given this miraculous sign, went out to meet him.</verse>
        <verse number="19">So the Pharisees said to one another, "See, this is getting us nowhere. Look how the whole world has gone after him!"</verse>
        <verse number="20">Now there were some Greeks among those who went up to worship at the Feast.</verse>
        <verse number="21">They came to Philip, who was from Bethsaida in Galilee, with a request. "Sir," they said, "we would like to see Jesus."</verse>
        <verse number="22">Philip went to tell Andrew; Andrew and Philip in turn told Jesus.</verse>
        <verse number="23">Jesus replied, "The hour has come for the Son of Man to be glorified.</verse>
        <verse number="24">I tell you the truth, unless a kernel of wheat falls to the ground and dies, it remains only a single seed. But if it dies, it produces many seeds.</verse>
        <verse number="25">The man who loves his life will lose it, while the man who hates his life in this world will keep it for eternal life.</verse>
        <verse number="26">Whoever serves me must follow me; and where I am, my servant also will be. My Father will honor the one who serves me.</verse>
        <verse number="27">"Now my heart is troubled, and what shall I say? 'Father, save me from this hour'? No, it was for this very reason I came to this hour.</verse>
        <verse number="28">Father, glorify your name!"</verse>
        <verse number="29">Then a voice came from heaven, "I have glorified it, and will glorify it again." The crowd that was there and heard it said it had thundered; others said an angel had spoken to him.</verse>
        <verse number="30">Jesus said, "This voice was for your benefit, not mine.</verse>
        <verse number="31">Now is the time for judgment on this world; now the prince of this world will be driven out.</verse>
        <verse number="32">But I, when I am lifted up from the earth, will draw all men to myself."</verse>
        <verse number="33">He said this to show the kind of death he was going to die.</verse>
        <verse number="34">The crowd spoke up, "We have heard from the Law that the Christ will remain forever, so how can you say, 'The Son of Man must be lifted up'? Who is this 'Son of Man'?"</verse>
        <verse number="35">Then Jesus told them, "You are going to have the light just a little while longer. Walk while you have the light, before darkness overtakes you. The man who walks in the dark does not know where he is going.</verse>
        <verse number="36">Put your trust in the light while you have it, so that you may become sons of light." When he had finished speaking, Jesus left and hid himself from them.</verse>
        <verse number="37">Even after Jesus had done all these miraculous signs in their presence, they still would not believe in him.</verse>
        <verse number="38">This was to fulfill the word of Isaiah the prophet: "Lord, who has believed our message and to whom has the arm of the Lord been revealed?"</verse>
        <verse number="39">For this reason they could not believe, because, as Isaiah says elsewhere:</verse>
        <verse number="40">"He has blinded their eyes and deadened their hearts, so they can neither see with their eyes, nor understand with their hearts, nor turn--and I would heal them."</verse>
        <verse number="41">Isaiah said this because he saw Jesus' glory and spoke about him.</verse>
        <verse number="42">Yet at the same time many even among the leaders believed in him. But because of the Pharisees they would not confess their faith for fear they would be put out of the synagogue;</verse>
        <verse number="43">for they loved praise from men more than praise from God.</verse>
        <verse number="44">Then Jesus cried out, "When a man believes in me, he does not believe in me only, but in the one who sent me.</verse>
        <verse number="45">When he looks at me, he sees the one who sent me.</verse>
        <verse number="46">I have come into the world as a light, so that no one who believes in me should stay in darkness.</verse>
        <verse number="47">"As for the person who hears my words but does not keep them, I do not judge him. For I did not come to judge the world, but to save it.</verse>
        <verse number="48">There is a judge for the one who rejects me and does not accept my words; that very word which I spoke will condemn him at the last day.</verse>
        <verse number="49">For I did not speak of my own accord, but the Father who sent me commanded me what to say and how to say it.</verse>
        <verse number="50">I know that his command leads to eternal life. So whatever I say is just what the Father has told me to say."</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter number="13">
        <verse number="1">It was just before the Passover Feast. Jesus knew that the time had come for him to leave this world and go to the Father. Having loved his own who were in the world, he now showed them the full extent of his love.</verse>
        <verse number="2">The evening meal was being served, and the devil had already prompted Judas Iscariot, son of Simon, to betray Jesus.</verse>
        <verse number="3">Jesus knew that the Father had put all things under his power, and that he had come from God and was returning to God;</verse>
        <verse number="4">so he got up from the meal, took off his outer clothing, and wrapped a towel around his waist.</verse>
        <verse number="5">After that, he poured water into a basin and began to wash his disciples' feet, drying them with the towel that was wrapped around him.</verse>
        <verse number="6">He came to Simon Peter, who said to him, "Lord, are you going to wash my feet?"</verse>
        <verse number="7">Jesus replied, "You do not realize now what I am doing, but later you will understand."</verse>
        <verse number="8">"No," said Peter, "you shall never wash my feet." Jesus answered, "Unless I wash you, you have no part with me."</verse>
        <verse number="9">"Then, Lord," Simon Peter replied, "not just my feet but my hands and my head as well!"</verse>
        <verse number="10">Jesus answered, "A person who has had a bath needs only to wash his feet; his whole body is clean. And you are clean, though not every one of you."</verse>
        <verse number="11">For he knew who was going to betray him, and that was why he said not every one was clean.</verse>
        <verse number="12">When he had finished washing their feet, he put on his clothes and returned to his place. "Do you understand what I have done for you?" he asked them.</verse>
        <verse number="13">"You call me 'Teacher' and 'Lord,' and rightly so, for that is what I am.</verse>
        <verse number="14">Now that I, your Lord and Teacher, have washed your feet, you also should wash one another's feet.</verse>
        <verse number="15">I have set you an example that you should do as I have done for you.</verse>
        <verse number="16">I tell you the truth, no servant is greater than his master, nor is a messenger greater than the one who sent him.</verse>
        <verse number="17">Now that you know these things, you will be blessed if you do them.</verse>
        <verse number="18">"I am not referring to all of you; I know those I have chosen. But this is to fulfill the scripture: 'He who shares my bread has lifted up his heel against me.'</verse>
        <verse number="19">"I am telling you now before it happens, so that when it does happen you will believe that I am He.</verse>
        <verse number="20">I tell you the truth, whoever accepts anyone I send accepts me; and whoever accepts me accepts the one who sent me."</verse>
        <verse number="21">After he had said this, Jesus was troubled in spirit and testified, "I tell you the truth, one of you is going to betray me."</verse>
        <verse number="22">His disciples stared at one another, at a loss to know which of them he meant.</verse>
        <verse number="23">One of them, the disciple whom Jesus loved, was reclining next to him.</verse>
        <verse number="24">Simon Peter motioned to this disciple and said, "Ask him which one he means."</verse>
        <verse number="25">Leaning back against Jesus, he asked him, "Lord, who is it?"</verse>
        <verse number="26">Jesus answered, "It is the one to whom I will give this piece of bread when I have dipped it in the dish." Then, dipping the piece of bread, he gave it to Judas Iscariot, son of Simon.</verse>
        <verse number="27">As soon as Judas took the bread, Satan entered into him.</verse>
        <verse number="28">"What you are about to do, do quickly," Jesus told him, but no one at the meal understood why Jesus said this to him.</verse>
        <verse number="29">Since Judas had charge of the money, some thought Jesus was telling him to buy what was needed for the Feast, or to give something to the poor.</verse>
        <verse number="30">As soon as Judas had taken the bread, he went out. And it was night.</verse>
        <verse number="31">When he was gone, Jesus said, "Now is the Son of Man glorified and God is glorified in him.</verse>
        <verse number="32">If God is glorified in him, God will glorify the Son in himself, and will glorify him at once.</verse>
        <verse number="33">"My children, I will be with you only a little longer. You will look for me, and just as I told the Jews, so I tell you now: Where I am going, you cannot come.</verse>
        <verse number="34">"A new command I give you: Love one another. As I have loved you, so you must love one another.</verse>
        <verse number="35">By this all men will know that you are my disciples, if you love one another."</verse>
        <verse number="36">Simon Peter asked him, "Lord, where are you going?" Jesus replied, "Where I am going, you cannot follow now, but you will follow later."</verse>
        <verse number="37">Peter asked, "Lord, why can't I follow you now? I will lay down my life for you."</verse>
        <verse number="38">Then Jesus answered, "Will you really lay down your life for me? I tell you the truth, before the rooster crows, you will disown me three times!</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter number="14">
        <verse number="1">"Do not let your hearts be troubled. Trust in God; trust also in me.</verse>
        <verse number="2">In my Father's house are many rooms; if it were not so, I would have told you. I am going there to prepare a place for you.</verse>
        <verse number="3">And if I go and prepare a place for you, I will come back and take you to be with me that you also may be where I am.</verse>
        <verse number="4">You know the way to the place where I am going."</verse>
        <verse number="5">Thomas said to him, "Lord, we don't know where you are going, so how can we know the way?"</verse>
        <verse number="6">Jesus answered, "I am the way and the truth and the life. No one comes to the Father except through me.</verse>
        <verse number="7">If you really knew me, you would know my Father as well. From now on, you do know him and have seen him."</verse>
        <verse number="8">Philip said, "Lord, show us the Father and that will be enough for us."</verse>
        <verse number="9">Jesus answered: "Don't you know me, Philip, even after I have been among you such a long time? Anyone who has seen me has seen the Father. How can you say, 'Show us the Father'?</verse>
        <verse number="10">Don't you believe that I am in the Father, and that the Father is in me? The words I say to you are not just my own. Rather, it is the Father, living in me, who is doing his work.</verse>
        <verse number="11">Believe me when I say that I am in the Father and the Father is in me; or at least believe on the evidence of the miracles themselves.</verse>
        <verse number="12">I tell you the truth, anyone who has faith in me will do what I have been doing. He will do even greater things than these, because I am going to the Father.</verse>
        <verse number="13">And I will do whatever you ask in my name, so that the Son may bring glory to the Father.</verse>
        <verse number="14">You may ask me for anything in my name, and I will do it.</verse>
        <verse number="15">"If you love me, you will obey what I command.</verse>
        <verse number="16">And I will ask the Father, and he will give you another Counselor to be with you forever--</verse>
        <verse number="17">the Spirit of truth. The world cannot accept him, because it neither sees him nor knows him. But you know him, for he lives with you and will be in you.</verse>
        <verse number="18">I will not leave you as orphans; I will come to you.</verse>
        <verse number="19">Before long, the world will not see me anymore, but you will see me. Because I live, you also will live.</verse>
        <verse number="20">On that day you will realize that I am in my Father, and you are in me, and I am in you.</verse>
        <verse number="21">Whoever has my commands and obeys them, he is the one who loves me. He who loves me will be loved by my Father, and I too will love him and show myself to him."</verse>
        <verse number="22">Then Judas (not Judas Iscariot) said, "But, Lord, why do you intend to show yourself to us and not to the world?"</verse>
        <verse number="23">Jesus replied, "If anyone loves me, he will obey my teaching. My Father will love him, and we will come to him and make our home with him.</verse>
        <verse number="24">He who does not love me will not obey my teaching. These words you hear are not my own; they belong to the Father who sent me.</verse>
        <verse number="25">"All this I have spoken while still with you.</verse>
        <verse number="26">But the Counselor, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in my name, will teach you all things and will remind you of everything I have said to you.</verse>
        <verse number="27">Peace I leave with you; my peace I give you. I do not give to you as the world gives. Do not let your hearts be troubled and do not be afraid.</verse>
        <verse number="28">"You heard me say, 'I am going away and I am coming back to you.' If you loved me, you would be glad that I am going to the Father, for the Father is greater than I.</verse>
        <verse number="29">I have told you now before it happens, so that when it does happen you will believe.</verse>
        <verse number="30">I will not speak with you much longer, for the prince of this world is coming. He has no hold on me,</verse>
        <verse number="31">but the world must learn that I love the Father and that I do exactly what my Father has commanded me. "Come now; let us leave.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter number="15">
        <verse number="1">"I am the true vine, and my Father is the gardener.</verse>
        <verse number="2">He cuts off every branch in me that bears no fruit, while every branch that does bear fruit he prunes so that it will be even more fruitful.</verse>
        <verse number="3">You are already clean because of the word I have spoken to you.</verse>
        <verse number="4">Remain in me, and I will remain in you. No branch can bear fruit by itself; it must remain in the vine. Neither can you bear fruit unless you remain in me.</verse>
        <verse number="5">"I am the vine; you are the branches. If a man remains in me and I in him, he will bear much fruit; apart from me you can do nothing.</verse>
        <verse number="6">If anyone does not remain in me, he is like a branch that is thrown away and withers; such branches are picked up, thrown into the fire and burned.</verse>
        <verse number="7">If you remain in me and my words remain in you, ask whatever you wish, and it will be given you.</verse>
        <verse number="8">This is to my Father's glory, that you bear much fruit, showing yourselves to be my disciples.</verse>
        <verse number="9">"As the Father has loved me, so have I loved you. Now remain in my love.</verse>
        <verse number="10">If you obey my commands, you will remain in my love, just as I have obeyed my Father's commands and remain in his love.</verse>
        <verse number="11">I have told you this so that my joy may be in you and that your joy may be complete.</verse>
        <verse number="12">My command is this: Love each other as I have loved you.</verse>
        <verse number="13">Greater love has no one than this, that he lay down his life for his friends.</verse>
        <verse number="14">You are my friends if you do what I command.</verse>
        <verse number="15">I no longer call you servants, because a servant does not know his master's business. Instead, I have called you friends, for everything that I learned from my Father I have made known to you.</verse>
        <verse number="16">You did not choose me, but I chose you and appointed you to go and bear fruit--fruit that will last. Then the Father will give you whatever you ask in my name.</verse>
        <verse number="17">This is my command: Love each other.</verse>
        <verse number="18">"If the world hates you, keep in mind that it hated me first.</verse>
        <verse number="19">If you belonged to the world, it would love you as its own. As it is, you do not belong to the world, but I have chosen you out of the world. That is why the world hates you.</verse>
        <verse number="20">Remember the words I spoke to you: 'No servant is greater than his master.' If they persecuted me, they will persecute you also. If they obeyed my teaching, they will obey yours also.</verse>
        <verse number="21">They will treat you this way because of my name, for they do not know the One who sent me.</verse>
        <verse number="22">If I had not come and spoken to them, they would not be guilty of sin. Now, however, they have no excuse for their sin.</verse>
        <verse number="23">He who hates me hates my Father as well.</verse>
        <verse number="24">If I had not done among them what no one else did, they would not be guilty of sin. But now they have seen these miracles, and yet they have hated both me and my Father.</verse>
        <verse number="25">But this is to fulfill what is written in their Law: 'They hated me without reason.'</verse>
        <verse number="26">"When the Counselor comes, whom I will send to you from the Father, the Spirit of truth who goes out from the Father, he will testify about me.</verse>
        <verse number="27">And you also must testify, for you have been with me from the beginning.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter number="16">
        <verse number="1">"All this I have told you so that you will not go astray.</verse>
        <verse number="2">They will put you out of the synagogue; in fact, a time is coming when anyone who kills you will think he is offering a service to God.</verse>
        <verse number="3">They will do such things because they have not known the Father or me.</verse>
        <verse number="4">I have told you this, so that when the time comes you will remember that I warned you. I did not tell you this at first because I was with you.</verse>
        <verse number="5">"Now I am going to him who sent me, yet none of you asks me, 'Where are you going?'</verse>
        <verse number="6">Because I have said these things, you are filled with grief.</verse>
        <verse number="7">But I tell you the truth: It is for your good that I am going away. Unless I go away, the Counselor will not come to you; but if I go, I will send him to you.</verse>
        <verse number="8">When he comes, he will convict the world of guilt in regard to sin and righteousness and judgment:</verse>
        <verse number="9">in regard to sin, because men do not believe in me;</verse>
        <verse number="10">in regard to righteousness, because I am going to the Father, where you can see me no longer;</verse>
        <verse number="11">and in regard to judgment, because the prince of this world now stands condemned.</verse>
        <verse number="12">"I have much more to say to you, more than you can now bear.</verse>
        <verse number="13">But when he, the Spirit of truth, comes, he will guide you into all truth. He will not speak on his own; he will speak only what he hears, and he will tell you what is yet to come.</verse>
        <verse number="14">He will bring glory to me by taking from what is mine and making it known to you.</verse>
        <verse number="15">All that belongs to the Father is mine. That is why I said the Spirit will take from what is mine and make it known to you.</verse>
        <verse number="16">"In a little while you will see me no more, and then after a little while you will see me."</verse>
        <verse number="17">Some of his disciples said to one another, "What does he mean by saying, 'In a little while you will see me no more, and then after a little while you will see me,' and 'Because I am going to the Father'?"</verse>
        <verse number="18">They kept asking, "What does he mean by 'a little while'? We don't understand what he is saying."</verse>
        <verse number="19">Jesus saw that they wanted to ask him about this, so he said to them, "Are you asking one another what I meant when I said, 'In a little while you will see me no more, and then after a little while you will see me'?</verse>
        <verse number="20">I tell you the truth, you will weep and mourn while the world rejoices. You will grieve, but your grief will turn to joy.</verse>
        <verse number="21">A woman giving birth to a child has pain because her time has come; but when her baby is born she forgets the anguish because of her joy that a child is born into the world.</verse>
        <verse number="22">So with you: Now is your time of grief, but I will see you again and you will rejoice, and no one will take away your joy.</verse>
        <verse number="23">In that day you will no longer ask me anything. I tell you the truth, my Father will give you whatever you ask in my name.</verse>
        <verse number="24">Until now you have not asked for anything in my name. Ask and you will receive, and your joy will be complete.</verse>
        <verse number="25">"Though I have been speaking figuratively, a time is coming when I will no longer use this kind of language but will tell you plainly about my Father.</verse>
        <verse number="26">In that day you will ask in my name. I am not saying that I will ask the Father on your behalf.</verse>
        <verse number="27">No, the Father himself loves you because you have loved me and have believed that I came from God.</verse>
        <verse number="28">I came from the Father and entered the world; now I am leaving the world and going back to the Father."</verse>
        <verse number="29">Then Jesus' disciples said, "Now you are speaking clearly and without figures of speech.</verse>
        <verse number="30">Now we can see that you know all things and that you do not even need to have anyone ask you questions. This makes us believe that you came from God."</verse>
        <verse number="31">"You believe at last!" Jesus answered.</verse>
        <verse number="32">"But a time is coming, and has come, when you will be scattered, each to his own home. You will leave me all alone. Yet I am not alone, for my Father is with me.</verse>
        <verse number="33">"I have told you these things, so that in me you may have peace. In this world you will have trouble. But take heart! I have overcome the world."</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter number="17">
        <verse number="1">After Jesus said this, he looked toward heaven and prayed:</verse>
        <verse number="2">"Father, the time has come. Glorify your Son, that your Son may glorify you. For you granted him authority over all people that he might give eternal life to all those you have given him.</verse>
        <verse number="3">Now this is eternal life: that they may know you, the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom you have sent.</verse>
        <verse number="4">I have brought you glory on earth by completing the work you gave me to do.</verse>
        <verse number="5">And now, Father, glorify me in your presence with the glory I had with you before the world began.</verse>
        <verse number="6">"I have revealed you to those whom you gave me out of the world. They were yours; you gave them to me and they have obeyed your word.</verse>
        <verse number="7">Now they know that everything you have given me comes from you.</verse>
        <verse number="8">For I gave them the words you gave me and they accepted them. They knew with certainty that I came from you, and they believed that you sent me.</verse>
        <verse number="9">I pray for them. I am not praying for the world, but for those you have given me, for they are yours.</verse>
        <verse number="10">All I have is yours, and all you have is mine. And glory has come to me through them.</verse>
        <verse number="11">I will remain in the world no longer, but they are still in the world, and I am coming to you. Holy Father, protect them by the power of your name--the name you gave me--so that they may be one as we are one.</verse>
        <verse number="12">While I was with them, I protected them and kept them safe by that name you gave me. None has been lost except the one doomed to destruction so that Scripture would be fulfilled.</verse>
        <verse number="13">"I am coming to you now, but I say these things while I am still in the world, so that they may have the full measure of my joy within them.</verse>
        <verse number="14">I have given them your word and the world has hated them, for they are not of the world any more than I am of the world.</verse>
        <verse number="15">My prayer is not that you take them out of the world but that you protect them from the evil one.</verse>
        <verse number="16">They are not of the world, even as I am not of it.</verse>
        <verse number="17">Sanctify them by the truth; your word is truth.</verse>
        <verse number="18">As you sent me into the world, I have sent them into the world.</verse>
        <verse number="19">For them I sanctify myself, that they too may be truly sanctified.</verse>
        <verse number="20">"My prayer is not for them alone. I pray also for those who will believe in me through their message,</verse>
        <verse number="21">that all of them may be one, Father, just as you are in me and I am in you. May they also be in us so that the world may believe that you have sent me.</verse>
        <verse number="22">I have given them the glory that you gave me, that they may be one as we are one:</verse>
        <verse number="23">I in them and you in me. May they be brought to complete unity to let the world know that you sent me and have loved them even as you have loved me.</verse>
        <verse number="24">"Father, I want those you have given me to be with me where I am, and to see my glory, the glory you have given me because you loved me before the creation of the world.</verse>
        <verse number="25">"Righteous Father, though the world does not know you, I know you, and they know that you have sent me.</verse>
        <verse number="26">I have made you known to them, and will continue to make you known in order that the love you have for me may be in them and that I myself may be in them."</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter number="18">
        <verse number="1">When he had finished praying, Jesus left with his disciples and crossed the Kidron Valley. On the other side there was an olive grove, and he and his disciples went into it.</verse>
        <verse number="2">Now Judas, who betrayed him, knew the place, because Jesus had often met there with his disciples.</verse>
        <verse number="3">So Judas came to the grove, guiding a detachment of soldiers and some officials from the chief priests and Pharisees. They were carrying torches, lanterns and weapons.</verse>
        <verse number="4">Jesus, knowing all that was going to happen to him, went out and asked them, "Who is it you want?"</verse>
        <verse number="5">"Jesus of Nazareth," they replied.</verse>
        <verse number="6">"I am he," Jesus said. (And Judas the traitor was standing there with them.) When Jesus said, "I am he," they drew back and fell to the ground.</verse>
        <verse number="7">Again he asked them, "Who is it you want?" And they said, "Jesus of Nazareth."</verse>
        <verse number="8">"I told you that I am he," Jesus answered. "If you are looking for me, then let these men go."</verse>
        <verse number="9">This happened so that the words he had spoken would be fulfilled: "I have not lost one of those you gave me."</verse>
        <verse number="10">Then Simon Peter, who had a sword, drew it and struck the high priest's servant, cutting off his right ear. (The servant's name was Malchus.)</verse>
        <verse number="11">Jesus commanded Peter, "Put your sword away! Shall I not drink the cup the Father has given me?"</verse>
        <verse number="12">Then the detachment of soldiers with its commander and the Jewish officials arrested Jesus. They bound him</verse>
        <verse number="13">and brought him first to Annas, who was the father-in-law of Caiaphas, the high priest that year.</verse>
        <verse number="14">Caiaphas was the one who had advised the Jews that it would be good if one man died for the people.</verse>
        <verse number="15">Simon Peter and another disciple were following Jesus. Because this disciple was known to the high priest, he went with Jesus into the high priest's courtyard,</verse>
        <verse number="16">but Peter had to wait outside at the door. The other disciple, who was known to the high priest, came back, spoke to the girl on duty there and brought Peter in.</verse>
        <verse number="17">"You are not one of his disciples, are you?" the girl at the door asked Peter. He replied, "I am not."</verse>
        <verse number="18">It was cold, and the servants and officials stood around a fire they had made to keep warm. Peter also was standing with them, warming himself.</verse>
        <verse number="19">Meanwhile, the high priest questioned Jesus about his disciples and his teaching.</verse>
        <verse number="20">"I have spoken openly to the world," Jesus replied. "I always taught in synagogues or at the temple, where all the Jews come together. I said nothing in secret.</verse>
        <verse number="21">Why question me? Ask those who heard me. Surely they know what I said."</verse>
        <verse number="22">When Jesus said this, one of the officials nearby struck him in the face. "Is this the way you answer the high priest?" he demanded.</verse>
        <verse number="23">"If I said something wrong," Jesus replied, "testify as to what is wrong. But if I spoke the truth, why did you strike me?"</verse>
        <verse number="24">Then Annas sent him, still bound, to Caiaphas the high priest.</verse>
        <verse number="25">As Simon Peter stood warming himself, he was asked, "You are not one of his disciples, are you?" He denied it, saying, "I am not."</verse>
        <verse number="26">One of the high priest's servants, a relative of the man whose ear Peter had cut off, challenged him, "Didn't I see you with him in the olive grove?"</verse>
        <verse number="27">Again Peter denied it, and at that moment a rooster began to crow.</verse>
        <verse number="28">Then the Jews led Jesus from Caiaphas to the palace of the Roman governor. By now it was early morning, and to avoid ceremonial uncleanness the Jews did not enter the palace; they wanted to be able to eat the Passover.</verse>
        <verse number="29">So Pilate came out to them and asked, "What charges are you bringing against this man?"</verse>
        <verse number="30">"If he were not a criminal," they replied, "we would not have handed him over to you."</verse>
        <verse number="31">Pilate said, "Take him yourselves and judge him by your own law."</verse>
        <verse number="32">"But we have no right to execute anyone," the Jews objected. This happened so that the words Jesus had spoken indicating the kind of death he was going to die would be fulfilled.</verse>
        <verse number="33">Pilate then went back inside the palace, summoned Jesus and asked him, "Are you the king of the Jews?"</verse>
        <verse number="34">"Is that your own idea," Jesus asked, "or did others talk to you about me?"</verse>
        <verse number="35">"Am I a Jew?" Pilate replied. "It was your people and your chief priests who handed you over to me. What is it you have done?"</verse>
        <verse number="36">Jesus said, "My kingdom is not of this world. If it were, my servants would fight to prevent my arrest by the Jews. But now my kingdom is from another place."</verse>
        <verse number="37">"You are a king, then!" said Pilate. Jesus answered, "You are right in saying I am a king. In fact, for this reason I was born, and for this I came into the world, to testify to the truth. Everyone on the side of truth listens to me."</verse>
        <verse number="38">"What is truth?" Pilate asked. With this he went out again to the Jews and said, "I find no basis for a charge against him.</verse>
        <verse number="39">But it is your custom for me to release to you one prisoner at the time of the Passover. Do you want me to release 'the king of the Jews'?"</verse>
        <verse number="40">They shouted back, "No, not him! Give us Barabbas!" Now Barabbas had taken part in a rebellion.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter number="19">
        <verse number="1">Then Pilate took Jesus and had him flogged.</verse>
        <verse number="2">The soldiers twisted together a crown of thorns and put it on his head. They clothed him in a purple robe</verse>
        <verse number="3">and went up to him again and again, saying, "Hail, king of the Jews!" And they struck him in the face.</verse>
        <verse number="4">Once more Pilate came out and said to the Jews, "Look, I am bringing him out to you to let you know that I find no basis for a charge against him."</verse>
        <verse number="5">When Jesus came out wearing the crown of thorns and the purple robe, Pilate said to them, "Here is the man!"</verse>
        <verse number="6">As soon as the chief priests and their officials saw him, they shouted, "Crucify! Crucify!" But Pilate answered, "You take him and crucify him. As for me, I find no basis for a charge against him."</verse>
        <verse number="7">The Jews insisted, "We have a law, and according to that law he must die, because he claimed to be the Son of God."</verse>
        <verse number="8">When Pilate heard this, he was even more afraid,</verse>
        <verse number="9">and he went back inside the palace. "Where do you come from?" he asked Jesus, but Jesus gave him no answer.</verse>
        <verse number="10">"Do you refuse to speak to me?" Pilate said. "Don't you realize I have power either to free you or to crucify you?"</verse>
        <verse number="11">Jesus answered, "You would have no power over me if it were not given to you from above. Therefore the one who handed me over to you is guilty of a greater sin."</verse>
        <verse number="12">From then on, Pilate tried to set Jesus free, but the Jews kept shouting, "If you let this man go, you are no friend of Caesar. Anyone who claims to be a king opposes Caesar."</verse>
        <verse number="13">When Pilate heard this, he brought Jesus out and sat down on the judge's seat at a place known as the Stone Pavement (which in Aramaic is Gabbatha).</verse>
        <verse number="14">It was the day of Preparation of Passover Week, about the sixth hour. "Here is your king," Pilate said to the Jews.</verse>
        <verse number="15">But they shouted, "Take him away! Take him away! Crucify him!Shall I crucify your king?" Pilate asked. "We have no king but Caesar," the chief priests answered.</verse>
        <verse number="16">Finally Pilate handed him over to them to be crucified.</verse>
        <verse number="17">So the soldiers took charge of Jesus. Carrying his own cross, he went out to the place of the Skull (which in Aramaic is called Golgotha).</verse>
        <verse number="18">Here they crucified him, and with him two others--one on each side and Jesus in the middle.</verse>
        <verse number="19">Pilate had a notice prepared and fastened to the cross. It read:|sc JESUS OF NAZARETH, THE KING OF THE JEWS.</verse>
        <verse number="20">Many of the Jews read this sign, for the place where Jesus was crucified was near the city, and the sign was written in Aramaic, Latin and Greek.</verse>
        <verse number="21">The chief priests of the Jews protested to Pilate, "Do not write 'The King of the Jews,' but that this man claimed to be king of the Jews."</verse>
        <verse number="22">Pilate answered, "What I have written, I have written."</verse>
        <verse number="23">When the soldiers crucified Jesus, they took his clothes, dividing them into four shares, one for each of them, with the undergarment remaining. This garment was seamless, woven in one piece from top to bottom.</verse>
        <verse number="24">"Let's not tear it," they said to one another. "Let's decide by lot who will get it." This happened that the scripture might be fulfilled which said, "They divided my garments among them and cast lots for my clothing." So this is what the soldiers did.</verse>
        <verse number="25">Near the cross of Jesus stood his mother, his mother's sister, Mary the wife of Clopas, and Mary Magdalene.</verse>
        <verse number="26">When Jesus saw his mother there, and the disciple whom he loved standing nearby, he said to his mother, "Dear woman, here is your son,"</verse>
        <verse number="27">and to the disciple, "Here is your mother." From that time on, this disciple took her into his home.</verse>
        <verse number="28">Later, knowing that all was now completed, and so that the Scripture would be fulfilled, Jesus said, "I am thirsty."</verse>
        <verse number="29">A jar of wine vinegar was there, so they soaked a sponge in it, put the sponge on a stalk of the hyssop plant, and lifted it to Jesus' lips.</verse>
        <verse number="30">When he had received the drink, Jesus said, "It is finished." With that, he bowed his head and gave up his spirit.</verse>
        <verse number="31">Now it was the day of Preparation, and the next day was to be a special Sabbath. Because the Jews did not want the bodies left on the crosses during the Sabbath, they asked Pilate to have the legs broken and the bodies taken down.</verse>
        <verse number="32">The soldiers therefore came and broke the legs of the first man who had been crucified with Jesus, and then those of the other.</verse>
        <verse number="33">But when they came to Jesus and found that he was already dead, they did not break his legs.</verse>
        <verse number="34">Instead, one of the soldiers pierced Jesus' side with a spear, bringing a sudden flow of blood and water.</verse>
        <verse number="35">The man who saw it has given testimony, and his testimony is true. He knows that he tells the truth, and he testifies so that you also may believe.</verse>
        <verse number="36">These things happened so that the scripture would be fulfilled: "Not one of his bones will be broken,"</verse>
        <verse number="37">and, as another scripture says, "They will look on the one they have pierced."</verse>
        <verse number="38">Later, Joseph of Arimathea asked Pilate for the body of Jesus. Now Joseph was a disciple of Jesus, but secretly because he feared the Jews. With Pilate's permission, he came and took the body away.</verse>
        <verse number="39">He was accompanied by Nicodemus, the man who earlier had visited Jesus at night. Nicodemus brought a mixture of myrrh and aloes, about seventy-five pounds.</verse>
        <verse number="40">Taking Jesus' body, the two of them wrapped it, with the spices, in strips of linen. This was in accordance with Jewish burial customs.</verse>
        <verse number="41">At the place where Jesus was crucified, there was a garden, and in the garden a new tomb, in which no one had ever been laid.</verse>
        <verse number="42">Because it was the Jewish day of Preparation and since the tomb was nearby, they laid Jesus there.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </book>
  </testament>
</bible>
