<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bible translation="English NIV">
  <testament name="New">
    <book name="Matthew">
      <chapter number="21">
        <verse number="1">As they approached Jerusalem and came to Bethphage on the Mount of Olives, Jesus sent two disciples,</verse>
        <verse number="2">saying to them, "Go to the village ahead of you, and at once you will find a donkey tied there, with her colt by her. Untie them and bring them to me.</verse>
        <verse number="3">If anyone says anything to you, tell him that the Lord needs them, and he will send them right away."</verse>
        <verse number="4">This took place to fulfill what was spoken through the prophet:</verse>
        <verse number="5">"Say to the Daughter of Zion, 'See, your king comes to you, gentle and riding on a donkey, on a colt, the foal of a donkey.'"</verse>
        <verse number="6">The disciples went and did as Jesus had instructed them.</verse>
        <verse number="7">They brought the donkey and the colt, placed their cloaks on them, and Jesus sat on them.</verse>
        <verse number="8">A very large crowd spread their cloaks on the road, while others cut branches from the trees and spread them on the road.</verse>
        <verse number="9">The crowds that went ahead of him and those that followed shouted, "Hosanna to the Son of David!Blessed is he who comes in the name of the Lord!Hosanna in the highest!"</verse>
        <verse number="10">When Jesus entered Jerusalem, the whole city was stirred and asked, "Who is this?"</verse>
        <verse number="11">The crowds answered, "This is Jesus, the prophet from Nazareth in Galilee."</verse>
        <verse number="12">Jesus entered the temple area and drove out all who were buying and selling there. He overturned the tables of the money changers and the benches of those selling doves.</verse>
        <verse number="13">"It is written," he said to them, "'My house will be called a house of prayer,' but you are making it a 'den of robbers.'"</verse>
        <verse number="14">The blind and the lame came to him at the temple, and he healed them.</verse>
        <verse number="15">But when the chief priests and the teachers of the law saw the wonderful things he did and the children shouting in the temple area, "Hosanna to the Son of David," they were indignant.</verse>
        <verse number="16">"Do you hear what these children are saying?" they asked him. "Yes," replied Jesus, "have you never read, "'From the lips of children and infants you have ordained praise'?"</verse>
        <verse number="17">And he left them and went out of the city to Bethany, where he spent the night.</verse>
        <verse number="18">Early in the morning, as he was on his way back to the city, he was hungry.</verse>
        <verse number="19">Seeing a fig tree by the road, he went up to it but found nothing on it except leaves. Then he said to it, "May you never bear fruit again!" Immediately the tree withered.</verse>
        <verse number="20">When the disciples saw this, they were amazed. "How did the fig tree wither so quickly?" they asked.</verse>
        <verse number="21">Jesus replied, "I tell you the truth, if you have faith and do not doubt, not only can you do what was done to the fig tree, but also you can say to this mountain, 'Go, throw yourself into the sea,' and it will be done.</verse>
        <verse number="22">If you believe, you will receive whatever you ask for in prayer."</verse>
        <verse number="23">Jesus entered the temple courts, and, while he was teaching, the chief priests and the elders of the people came to him. "By what authority are you doing these things?" they asked. "And who gave you this authority?"</verse>
        <verse number="24">Jesus replied, "I will also ask you one question. If you answer me, I will tell you by what authority I am doing these things.</verse>
        <verse number="25">John's baptism--where did it come from? Was it from heaven, or from men?"</verse>
        <verse number="26">They discussed it among themselves and said, "If we say, 'From heaven,' he will ask, 'Then why didn't you believe him?' But if we say, 'From men'--we are afraid of the people, for they all hold that John was a prophet."</verse>
        <verse number="27">So they answered Jesus, "We don't know." Then he said, "Neither will I tell you by what authority I am doing these things.</verse>
        <verse number="28">"What do you think? There was a man who had two sons. He went to the first and said, 'Son, go and work today in the vineyard.'</verse>
        <verse number="29">"'I will not,' he answered, but later he changed his mind and went.</verse>
        <verse number="30">"Then the father went to the other son and said the same thing. He answered, 'I will, sir,' but he did not go.</verse>
        <verse number="31">"Which of the two did what his father wanted?The first," they answered.</verse>
        <verse number="32">Jesus said to them, "I tell you the truth, the tax collectors and the prostitutes are entering the kingdom of God ahead of you. For John came to you to show you the way of righteousness, and you did not believe him, but the tax collectors and the prostitutes did. And even after you saw this, you did not repent and believe him.</verse>
        <verse number="33">"Listen to another parable: There was a landowner who planted a vineyard. He put a wall around it, dug a winepress in it and built a watchtower. Then he rented the vineyard to some farmers and went away on a journey.</verse>
        <verse number="34">When the harvest time approached, he sent his servants to the tenants to collect his fruit.</verse>
        <verse number="35">"The tenants seized his servants; they beat one, killed another, and stoned a third.</verse>
        <verse number="36">Then he sent other servants to them, more than the first time, and the tenants treated them the same way.</verse>
        <verse number="37">Last of all, he sent his son to them. 'They will respect my son,' he said.</verse>
        <verse number="38">"But when the tenants saw the son, they said to each other, 'This is the heir. Come, let's kill him and take his inheritance.'</verse>
        <verse number="39">So they took him and threw him out of the vineyard and killed him.</verse>
        <verse number="40">"Therefore, when the owner of the vineyard comes, what will he do to those tenants?"</verse>
        <verse number="41">"He will bring those wretches to a wretched end," they replied, "and he will rent the vineyard to other tenants, who will give him his share of the crop at harvest time."</verse>
        <verse number="42">Jesus said to them, "Have you never read in the Scriptures: "'The stone the builders rejected has become the capstone; the Lord has done this, and it is marvelous in our eyes'?</verse>
        <verse number="43">"Therefore I tell you that the kingdom of God will be taken away from you and given to a people who will produce its fruit.</verse>
        <verse number="44">He who falls on this stone will be broken to pieces, but he on whom it falls will be crushed."</verse>
        <verse number="45">When the chief priests and the Pharisees heard Jesus' parables, they knew he was talking about them.</verse>
        <verse number="46">They looked for a way to arrest him, but they were afraid of the crowd because the people held that he was a prophet.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter number="22">
        <verse number="1">Jesus spoke to them again in parables, saying:</verse>
        <verse number="2">"The kingdom of heaven is like a king who prepared a wedding banquet for his son.</verse>
        <verse number="3">He sent his servants to those who had been invited to the banquet to tell them to come, but they refused to come.</verse>
        <verse number="4">"Then he sent some more servants and said, 'Tell those who have been invited that I have prepared my dinner: My oxen and fattened cattle have been butchered, and everything is ready. Come to the wedding banquet.'</verse>
        <verse number="5">"But they paid no attention and went off--one to his field, another to his business.</verse>
        <verse number="6">The rest seized his servants, mistreated them and killed them.</verse>
        <verse number="7">The king was enraged. He sent his army and destroyed those murderers and burned their city.</verse>
        <verse number="8">"Then he said to his servants, 'The wedding banquet is ready, but those I invited did not deserve to come.</verse>
        <verse number="9">Go to the street corners and invite to the banquet anyone you find.'</verse>
        <verse number="10">So the servants went out into the streets and gathered all the people they could find, both good and bad, and the wedding hall was filled with guests.</verse>
        <verse number="11">"But when the king came in to see the guests, he noticed a man there who was not wearing wedding clothes.</verse>
        <verse number="12">'Friend,' he asked, 'how did you get in here without wedding clothes?' The man was speechless.</verse>
        <verse number="13">"Then the king told the attendants, 'Tie him hand and foot, and throw him outside, into the darkness, where there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.'</verse>
        <verse number="14">"For many are invited, but few are chosen."</verse>
        <verse number="15">Then the Pharisees went out and laid plans to trap him in his words.</verse>
        <verse number="16">They sent their disciples to him along with the Herodians. "Teacher," they said, "we know you are a man of integrity and that you teach the way of God in accordance with the truth. You aren't swayed by men, because you pay no attention to who they are.</verse>
        <verse number="17">Tell us then, what is your opinion? Is it right to pay taxes to Caesar or not?"</verse>
        <verse number="18">But Jesus, knowing their evil intent, said, "You hypocrites, why are you trying to trap me?</verse>
        <verse number="19">Show me the coin used for paying the tax." They brought him a denarius,</verse>
        <verse number="20">and he asked them, "Whose portrait is this? And whose inscription?"</verse>
        <verse number="21">"Caesar's," they replied. Then he said to them, "Give to Caesar what is Caesar's, and to God what is God's."</verse>
        <verse number="22">When they heard this, they were amazed. So they left him and went away.</verse>
        <verse number="23">That same day the Sadducees, who say there is no resurrection, came to him with a question.</verse>
        <verse number="24">"Teacher," they said, "Moses told us that if a man dies without having children, his brother must marry the widow and have children for him.</verse>
        <verse number="25">Now there were seven brothers among us. The first one married and died, and since he had no children, he left his wife to his brother.</verse>
        <verse number="26">The same thing happened to the second and third brother, right on down to the seventh.</verse>
        <verse number="27">Finally, the woman died.</verse>
        <verse number="28">Now then, at the resurrection, whose wife will she be of the seven, since all of them were married to her?"</verse>
        <verse number="29">Jesus replied, "You are in error because you do not know the Scriptures or the power of God.</verse>
        <verse number="30">At the resurrection people will neither marry nor be given in marriage; they will be like the angels in heaven.</verse>
        <verse number="31">But about the resurrection of the dead--have you not read what God said to you,</verse>
        <verse number="32">'I am the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob'? He is not the God of the dead but of the living."</verse>
        <verse number="33">When the crowds heard this, they were astonished at his teaching.</verse>
        <verse number="34">Hearing that Jesus had silenced the Sadducees, the Pharisees got together.</verse>
        <verse number="35">One of them, an expert in the law, tested him with this question:</verse>
        <verse number="36">"Teacher, which is the greatest commandment in the Law?"</verse>
        <verse number="37">Jesus replied: "'Love the Lord your God with all your heart and with all your soul and with all your mind.'</verse>
        <verse number="38">This is the first and greatest commandment.</verse>
        <verse number="39">And the second is like it: 'Love your neighbor as yourself.'</verse>
        <verse number="40">All the Law and the Prophets hang on these two commandments."</verse>
        <verse number="41">While the Pharisees were gathered together, Jesus asked them,</verse>
        <verse number="42">"What do you think about the Christ? Whose son is he?The son of David," they replied.</verse>
        <verse number="43">He said to them, "How is it then that David, speaking by the Spirit, calls him 'Lord'? For he says,</verse>
        <verse number="44">"'The Lord said to my Lord: "Sit at my right hand until I put your enemies under your feet."'</verse>
        <verse number="45">If then David calls him 'Lord,' how can he be his son?"</verse>
        <verse number="46">No one could say a word in reply, and from that day on no one dared to ask him any more questions.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter number="23">
        <verse number="1">Then Jesus said to the crowds and to his disciples:</verse>
        <verse number="2">"The teachers of the law and the Pharisees sit in Moses' seat.</verse>
        <verse number="3">So you must obey them and do everything they tell you. But do not do what they do, for they do not practice what they preach.</verse>
        <verse number="4">They tie up heavy loads and put them on men's shoulders, but they themselves are not willing to lift a finger to move them.</verse>
        <verse number="5">"Everything they do is done for men to see: They make their phylacteries wide and the tassels on their garments long;</verse>
        <verse number="6">they love the place of honor at banquets and the most important seats in the synagogues;</verse>
        <verse number="7">they love to be greeted in the marketplaces and to have men call them 'Rabbi.'</verse>
        <verse number="8">"But you are not to be called 'Rabbi,' for you have only one Master and you are all brothers.</verse>
        <verse number="9">And do not call anyone on earth 'father,' for you have one Father, and he is in heaven.</verse>
        <verse number="10">Nor are you to be called 'teacher,' for you have one Teacher, the Christ.</verse>
        <verse number="11">The greatest among you will be your servant.</verse>
        <verse number="12">For whoever exalts himself will be humbled, and whoever humbles himself will be exalted.</verse>
        <verse number="13">"Woe to you, teachers of the law and Pharisees, you hypocrites! You shut the kingdom of heaven in men's faces. You yourselves do not enter, nor will you let those enter who are trying to.</verse>
        <verse number="14">See Footnote</verse>
        <verse number="15">"Woe to you, teachers of the law and Pharisees, you hypocrites! You travel over land and sea to win a single convert, and when he becomes one, you make him twice as much a son of hell as you are.</verse>
        <verse number="16">"Woe to you, blind guides! You say, 'If anyone swears by the temple, it means nothing; but if anyone swears by the gold of the temple, he is bound by his oath.'</verse>
        <verse number="17">You blind fools! Which is greater: the gold, or the temple that makes the gold sacred?</verse>
        <verse number="18">You also say, 'If anyone swears by the altar, it means nothing; but if anyone swears by the gift on it, he is bound by his oath.'</verse>
        <verse number="19">You blind men! Which is greater: the gift, or the altar that makes the gift sacred?</verse>
        <verse number="20">Therefore, he who swears by the altar swears by it and by everything on it.</verse>
        <verse number="21">And he who swears by the temple swears by it and by the one who dwells in it.</verse>
        <verse number="22">And he who swears by heaven swears by God's throne and by the one who sits on it.</verse>
        <verse number="23">"Woe to you, teachers of the law and Pharisees, you hypocrites! You give a tenth of your spices--mint, dill and cummin. But you have neglected the more important matters of the law--justice, mercy and faithfulness. You should have practiced the latter, without neglecting the former.</verse>
        <verse number="24">You blind guides! You strain out a gnat but swallow a camel.</verse>
        <verse number="25">"Woe to you, teachers of the law and Pharisees, you hypocrites! You clean the outside of the cup and dish, but inside they are full of greed and self-indulgence.</verse>
        <verse number="26">Blind Pharisee! First clean the inside of the cup and dish, and then the outside also will be clean.</verse>
        <verse number="27">"Woe to you, teachers of the law and Pharisees, you hypocrites! You are like whitewashed tombs, which look beautiful on the outside but on the inside are full of dead men's bones and everything unclean.</verse>
        <verse number="28">In the same way, on the outside you appear to people as righteous but on the inside you are full of hypocrisy and wickedness.</verse>
        <verse number="29">"Woe to you, teachers of the law and Pharisees, you hypocrites! You build tombs for the prophets and decorate the graves of the righteous.</verse>
        <verse number="30">And you say, 'If we had lived in the days of our forefathers, we would not have taken part with them in shedding the blood of the prophets.'</verse>
        <verse number="31">So you testify against yourselves that you are the descendants of those who murdered the prophets.</verse>
        <verse number="32">Fill up, then, the measure of the sin of your forefathers!</verse>
        <verse number="33">"You snakes! You brood of vipers! How will you escape being condemned to hell?</verse>
        <verse number="34">Therefore I am sending you prophets and wise men and teachers. Some of them you will kill and crucify; others you will flog in your synagogues and pursue from town to town.</verse>
        <verse number="35">And so upon you will come all the righteous blood that has been shed on earth, from the blood of righteous Abel to the blood of Zechariah son of Berekiah, whom you murdered between the temple and the altar.</verse>
        <verse number="36">I tell you the truth, all this will come upon this generation.</verse>
        <verse number="37">"O Jerusalem, Jerusalem, you who kill the prophets and stone those sent to you, how often I have longed to gather your children together, as a hen gathers her chicks under her wings, but you were not willing.</verse>
        <verse number="38">Look, your house is left to you desolate.</verse>
        <verse number="39">For I tell you, you will not see me again until you say, 'Blessed is he who comes in the name of the Lord.'"</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter number="24">
        <verse number="1">Jesus left the temple and was walking away when his disciples came up to him to call his attention to its buildings.</verse>
        <verse number="2">"Do you see all these things?" he asked. "I tell you the truth, not one stone here will be left on another; every one will be thrown down."</verse>
        <verse number="3">As Jesus was sitting on the Mount of Olives, the disciples came to him privately. "Tell us," they said, "when will this happen, and what will be the sign of your coming and of the end of the age?"</verse>
        <verse number="4">Jesus answered: "Watch out that no one deceives you.</verse>
        <verse number="5">For many will come in my name, claiming, 'I am the Christ, 'and will deceive many.</verse>
        <verse number="6">You will hear of wars and rumors of wars, but see to it that you are not alarmed. Such things must happen, but the end is still to come.</verse>
        <verse number="7">Nation will rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom. There will be famines and earthquakes in various places.</verse>
        <verse number="8">All these are the beginning of birth pains.</verse>
        <verse number="9">"Then you will be handed over to be persecuted and put to death, and you will be hated by all nations because of me.</verse>
        <verse number="10">At that time many will turn away from the faith and will betray and hate each other,</verse>
        <verse number="11">and many false prophets will appear and deceive many people.</verse>
        <verse number="12">Because of the increase of wickedness, the love of most will grow cold,</verse>
        <verse number="13">but he who stands firm to the end will be saved.</verse>
        <verse number="14">And this gospel of the kingdom will be preached in the whole world as a testimony to all nations, and then the end will come.</verse>
        <verse number="15">"So when you see standing in the holy place 'the abomination that causes desolation,' spoken of through the prophet Daniel--let the reader understand--</verse>
        <verse number="16">then let those who are in Judea flee to the mountains.</verse>
        <verse number="17">Let no one on the roof of his house go down to take anything out of the house.</verse>
        <verse number="18">Let no one in the field go back to get his cloak.</verse>
        <verse number="19">How dreadful it will be in those days for pregnant women and nursing mothers!</verse>
        <verse number="20">Pray that your flight will not take place in winter or on the Sabbath.</verse>
        <verse number="21">For then there will be great distress, unequaled from the beginning of the world until now--and never to be equaled again.</verse>
        <verse number="22">If those days had not been cut short, no one would survive, but for the sake of the elect those days will be shortened.</verse>
        <verse number="23">At that time if anyone says to you, 'Look, here is the Christ!' or, 'There he is!' do not believe it.</verse>
        <verse number="24">For false Christs and false prophets will appear and perform great signs and miracles to deceive even the elect--if that were possible.</verse>
        <verse number="25">See, I have told you ahead of time.</verse>
        <verse number="26">"So if anyone tells you, 'There he is, out in the desert,' do not go out; or, 'Here he is, in the inner rooms,' do not believe it.</verse>
        <verse number="27">For as lightning that comes from the east is visible even in the west, so will be the coming of the Son of Man.</verse>
        <verse number="28">Wherever there is a carcass, there the vultures will gather.</verse>
        <verse number="29">"Immediately after the distress of those days "'the sun will be darkened, and the moon will not give its light; the stars will fall from the sky, and the heavenly bodies will be shaken.'</verse>
        <verse number="30">"At that time the sign of the Son of Man will appear in the sky, and all the nations of the earth will mourn. They will see the Son of Man coming on the clouds of the sky, with power and great glory.</verse>
        <verse number="31">And he will send his angels with a loud trumpet call, and they will gather his elect from the four winds, from one end of the heavens to the other.</verse>
        <verse number="32">"Now learn this lesson from the fig tree: As soon as its twigs get tender and its leaves come out, you know that summer is near.</verse>
        <verse number="33">Even so, when you see all these things, you know that it is near, right at the door.</verse>
        <verse number="34">I tell you the truth, this generation will certainly not pass away until all these things have happened.</verse>
        <verse number="35">Heaven and earth will pass away, but my words will never pass away.</verse>
        <verse number="36">"No one knows about that day or hour, not even the angels in heaven, nor the Son, but only the Father.</verse>
        <verse number="37">As it was in the days of Noah, so it will be at the coming of the Son of Man.</verse>
        <verse number="38">For in the days before the flood, people were eating and drinking, marrying and giving in marriage, up to the day Noah entered the ark;</verse>
        <verse number="39">and they knew nothing about what would happen until the flood came and took them all away. That is how it will be at the coming of the Son of Man.</verse>
        <verse number="40">Two men will be in the field; one will be taken and the other left.</verse>
        <verse number="41">Two women will be grinding with a hand mill; one will be taken and the other left.</verse>
        <verse number="42">"Therefore keep watch, because you do not know on what day your Lord will come.</verse>
        <verse number="43">But understand this: If the owner of the house had known at what time of night the thief was coming, he would have kept watch and would not have let his house be broken into.</verse>
        <verse number="44">So you also must be ready, because the Son of Man will come at an hour when you do not expect him.</verse>
        <verse number="45">"Who then is the faithful and wise servant, whom the master has put in charge of the servants in his household to give them their food at the proper time?</verse>
        <verse number="46">It will be good for that servant whose master finds him doing so when he returns.</verse>
        <verse number="47">I tell you the truth, he will put him in charge of all his possessions.</verse>
        <verse number="48">But suppose that servant is wicked and says to himself, 'My master is staying away a long time,'</verse>
        <verse number="49">and he then begins to beat his fellow servants and to eat and drink with drunkards.</verse>
        <verse number="50">The master of that servant will come on a day when he does not expect him and at an hour he is not aware of.</verse>
        <verse number="51">He will cut him to pieces and assign him a place with the hypocrites, where there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter number="25">
        <verse number="1">"At that time the kingdom of heaven will be like ten virgins who took their lamps and went out to meet the bridegroom.</verse>
        <verse number="2">Five of them were foolish and five were wise.</verse>
        <verse number="3">The foolish ones took their lamps but did not take any oil with them.</verse>
        <verse number="4">The wise, however, took oil in jars along with their lamps.</verse>
        <verse number="5">The bridegroom was a long time in coming, and they all became drowsy and fell asleep.</verse>
        <verse number="6">"At midnight the cry rang out: 'Here's the bridegroom! Come out to meet him!'</verse>
        <verse number="7">"Then all the virgins woke up and trimmed their lamps.</verse>
        <verse number="8">The foolish ones said to the wise, 'Give us some of your oil; our lamps are going out.'</verse>
        <verse number="9">"'No,' they replied, 'there may not be enough for both us and you. Instead, go to those who sell oil and buy some for yourselves.'</verse>
        <verse number="10">"But while they were on their way to buy the oil, the bridegroom arrived. The virgins who were ready went in with him to the wedding banquet. And the door was shut.</verse>
        <verse number="11">"Later the others also came. 'Sir! Sir!' they said. 'Open the door for us!'</verse>
        <verse number="12">"But he replied, 'I tell you the truth, I don't know you.'</verse>
        <verse number="13">"Therefore keep watch, because you do not know the day or the hour.</verse>
        <verse number="14">"Again, it will be like a man going on a journey, who called his servants and entrusted his property to them.</verse>
        <verse number="15">To one he gave five talents of money, to another two talents, and to another one talent, each according to his ability. Then he went on his journey.</verse>
        <verse number="16">The man who had received the five talents went at once and put his money to work and gained five more.</verse>
        <verse number="17">So also, the one with the two talents gained two more.</verse>
        <verse number="18">But the man who had received the one talent went off, dug a hole in the ground and hid his master's money.</verse>
        <verse number="19">"After a long time the master of those servants returned and settled accounts with them.</verse>
        <verse number="20">The man who had received the five talents brought the other five. 'Master,' he said, 'you entrusted me with five talents. See, I have gained five more.'</verse>
        <verse number="21">"His master replied, 'Well done, good and faithful servant! You have been faithful with a few things; I will put you in charge of many things. Come and share your master's happiness!'</verse>
        <verse number="22">"The man with the two talents also came. 'Master,' he said, 'you entrusted me with two talents; see, I have gained two more.'</verse>
        <verse number="23">"His master replied, 'Well done, good and faithful servant! You have been faithful with a few things; I will put you in charge of many things. Come and share your master's happiness!'</verse>
        <verse number="24">"Then the man who had received the one talent came. 'Master,' he said, 'I knew that you are a hard man, harvesting where you have not sown and gathering where you have not scattered seed.</verse>
        <verse number="25">So I was afraid and went out and hid your talent in the ground. See, here is what belongs to you.'</verse>
        <verse number="26">"His master replied, 'You wicked, lazy servant! So you knew that I harvest where I have not sown and gather where I have not scattered seed?</verse>
        <verse number="27">Well then, you should have put my money on deposit with the bankers, so that when I returned I would have received it back with interest.</verse>
        <verse number="28">"'Take the talent from him and give it to the one who has the ten talents.</verse>
        <verse number="29">For everyone who has will be given more, and he will have an abundance. Whoever does not have, even what he has will be taken from him.</verse>
        <verse number="30">And throw that worthless servant outside, into the darkness, where there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.'</verse>
        <verse number="31">"When the Son of Man comes in his glory, and all the angels with him, he will sit on his throne in heavenly glory.</verse>
        <verse number="32">All the nations will be gathered before him, and he will separate the people one from another as a shepherd separates the sheep from the goats.</verse>
        <verse number="33">He will put the sheep on his right and the goats on his left.</verse>
        <verse number="34">"Then the King will say to those on his right, 'Come, you who are blessed by my Father; take your inheritance, the kingdom prepared for you since the creation of the world.</verse>
        <verse number="35">For I was hungry and you gave me something to eat, I was thirsty and you gave me something to drink, I was a stranger and you invited me in,</verse>
        <verse number="36">I needed clothes and you clothed me, I was sick and you looked after me, I was in prison and you came to visit me.'</verse>
        <verse number="37">"Then the righteous will answer him, 'Lord, when did we see you hungry and feed you, or thirsty and give you something to drink?</verse>
        <verse number="38">When did we see you a stranger and invite you in, or needing clothes and clothe you?</verse>
        <verse number="39">When did we see you sick or in prison and go to visit you?'</verse>
        <verse number="40">"The King will reply, 'I tell you the truth, whatever you did for one of the least of these brothers of mine, you did for me.'</verse>
        <verse number="41">"Then he will say to those on his left, 'Depart from me, you who are cursed, into the eternal fire prepared for the devil and his angels.</verse>
        <verse number="42">For I was hungry and you gave me nothing to eat, I was thirsty and you gave me nothing to drink,</verse>
        <verse number="43">I was a stranger and you did not invite me in, I needed clothes and you did not clothe me, I was sick and in prison and you did not look after me.'</verse>
        <verse number="44">"They also will answer, 'Lord, when did we see you hungry or thirsty or a stranger or needing clothes or sick or in prison, and did not help you?'</verse>
        <verse number="45">"He will reply, 'I tell you the truth, whatever you did not do for one of the least of these, you did not do for me.'</verse>
        <verse number="46">"Then they will go away to eternal punishment, but the righteous to eternal life."</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter number="26">
        <verse number="1">When Jesus had finished saying all these things, he said to his disciples,</verse>
        <verse number="2">"As you know, the Passover is two days away--and the Son of Man will be handed over to be crucified."</verse>
        <verse number="3">Then the chief priests and the elders of the people assembled in the palace of the high priest, whose name was Caiaphas,</verse>
        <verse number="4">and they plotted to arrest Jesus in some sly way and kill him.</verse>
        <verse number="5">"But not during the Feast," they said, "or there may be a riot among the people."</verse>
        <verse number="6">While Jesus was in Bethany in the home of a man known as Simon the Leper,</verse>
        <verse number="7">a woman came to him with an alabaster jar of very expensive perfume, which she poured on his head as he was reclining at the table.</verse>
        <verse number="8">When the disciples saw this, they were indignant. "Why this waste?" they asked.</verse>
        <verse number="9">"This perfume could have been sold at a high price and the money given to the poor."</verse>
        <verse number="10">Aware of this, Jesus said to them, "Why are you bothering this woman? She has done a beautiful thing to me.</verse>
        <verse number="11">The poor you will always have with you, but you will not always have me.</verse>
        <verse number="12">When she poured this perfume on my body, she did it to prepare me for burial.</verse>
        <verse number="13">I tell you the truth, wherever this gospel is preached throughout the world, what she has done will also be told, in memory of her."</verse>
        <verse number="14">Then one of the Twelve--the one called Judas Iscariot--went to the chief priests</verse>
        <verse number="15">and asked, "What are you willing to give me if I hand him over to you?" So they counted out for him thirty silver coins.</verse>
        <verse number="16">From then on Judas watched for an opportunity to hand him over.</verse>
        <verse number="17">On the first day of the Feast of Unleavened Bread, the disciples came to Jesus and asked, "Where do you want us to make preparations for you to eat the Passover?"</verse>
        <verse number="18">He replied, "Go into the city to a certain man and tell him, 'The Teacher says: My appointed time is near. I am going to celebrate the Passover with my disciples at your house.'"</verse>
        <verse number="19">So the disciples did as Jesus had directed them and prepared the Passover.</verse>
        <verse number="20">When evening came, Jesus was reclining at the table with the Twelve.</verse>
        <verse number="21">And while they were eating, he said, "I tell you the truth, one of you will betray me."</verse>
        <verse number="22">They were very sad and began to say to him one after the other, "Surely not I, Lord?"</verse>
        <verse number="23">Jesus replied, "The one who has dipped his hand into the bowl with me will betray me.</verse>
        <verse number="24">The Son of Man will go just as it is written about him. But woe to that man who betrays the Son of Man! It would be better for him if he had not been born."</verse>
        <verse number="25">Then Judas, the one who would betray him, said, "Surely not I, Rabbi?" Jesus answered, "Yes, it is you."</verse>
        <verse number="26">While they were eating, Jesus took bread, gave thanks and broke it, and gave it to his disciples, saying, "Take and eat; this is my body."</verse>
        <verse number="27">Then he took the cup, gave thanks and offered it to them, saying, "Drink from it, all of you.</verse>
        <verse number="28">This is my blood of the covenant, which is poured out for many for the forgiveness of sins.</verse>
        <verse number="29">I tell you, I will not drink of this fruit of the vine from now on until that day when I drink it anew with you in my Father's kingdom."</verse>
        <verse number="30">When they had sung a hymn, they went out to the Mount of Olives.</verse>
        <verse number="31">Then Jesus told them, "This very night you will all fall away on account of me, for it is written: "'I will strike the shepherd, and the sheep of the flock will be scattered.'</verse>
        <verse number="32">But after I have risen, I will go ahead of you into Galilee."</verse>
        <verse number="33">Peter replied, "Even if all fall away on account of you, I never will."</verse>
        <verse number="34">"I tell you the truth," Jesus answered, "this very night, before the rooster crows, you will disown me three times."</verse>
        <verse number="35">But Peter declared, "Even if I have to die with you, I will never disown you." And all the other disciples said the same.</verse>
        <verse number="36">Then Jesus went with his disciples to a place called Gethsemane, and he said to them, "Sit here while I go over there and pray."</verse>
        <verse number="37">He took Peter and the two sons of Zebedee along with him, and he began to be sorrowful and troubled.</verse>
        <verse number="38">Then he said to them, "My soul is overwhelmed with sorrow to the point of death. Stay here and keep watch with me."</verse>
        <verse number="39">Going a little farther, he fell with his face to the ground and prayed, "My Father, if it is possible, may this cup be taken from me. Yet not as I will, but as you will."</verse>
        <verse number="40">Then he returned to his disciples and found them sleeping. "Could you men not keep watch with me for one hour?" he asked Peter.</verse>
        <verse number="41">"Watch and pray so that you will not fall into temptation. The spirit is willing, but the body is weak."</verse>
        <verse number="42">He went away a second time and prayed, "My Father, if it is not possible for this cup to be taken away unless I drink it, may your will be done."</verse>
        <verse number="43">When he came back, he again found them sleeping, because their eyes were heavy.</verse>
        <verse number="44">So he left them and went away once more and prayed the third time, saying the same thing.</verse>
        <verse number="45">Then he returned to the disciples and said to them, "Are you still sleeping and resting? Look, the hour is near, and the Son of Man is betrayed into the hands of sinners.</verse>
        <verse number="46">Rise, let us go! Here comes my betrayer!"</verse>
        <verse number="47">While he was still speaking, Judas, one of the Twelve, arrived. With him was a large crowd armed with swords and clubs, sent from the chief priests and the elders of the people.</verse>
        <verse number="48">Now the betrayer had arranged a signal with them: "The one I kiss is the man; arrest him."</verse>
        <verse number="49">Going at once to Jesus, Judas said, "Greetings, Rabbi!" and kissed him.</verse>
        <verse number="50">Jesus replied, "Friend, do what you came for."</verse>
        <verse number="51">Then the men stepped forward, seized Jesus and arrested him. With that, one of Jesus' companions reached for his sword, drew it out and struck the servant of the high priest, cutting off his ear.</verse>
        <verse number="52">"Put your sword back in its place," Jesus said to him, "for all who draw the sword will die by the sword.</verse>
        <verse number="53">Do you think I cannot call on my Father, and he will at once put at my disposal more than twelve legions of angels?</verse>
        <verse number="54">But how then would the Scriptures be fulfilled that say it must happen in this way?"</verse>
        <verse number="55">At that time Jesus said to the crowd, "Am I leading a rebellion, that you have come out with swords and clubs to capture me? Every day I sat in the temple courts teaching, and you did not arrest me.</verse>
        <verse number="56">But this has all taken place that the writings of the prophets might be fulfilled." Then all the disciples deserted him and fled.</verse>
        <verse number="57">Those who had arrested Jesus took him to Caiaphas, the high priest, where the teachers of the law and the elders had assembled.</verse>
        <verse number="58">But Peter followed him at a distance, right up to the courtyard of the high priest. He entered and sat down with the guards to see the outcome.</verse>
        <verse number="59">The chief priests and the whole Sanhedrin were looking for false evidence against Jesus so that they could put him to death.</verse>
        <verse number="60">But they did not find any, though many false witnesses came forward.</verse>
        <verse number="61">Finally two came forward and declared, "This fellow said, 'I am able to destroy the temple of God and rebuild it in three days.'"</verse>
        <verse number="62">Then the high priest stood up and said to Jesus, "Are you not going to answer? What is this testimony that these men are bringing against you?"</verse>
        <verse number="63">But Jesus remained silent. The high priest said to him, "I charge you under oath by the living God: Tell us if you are the Christ, the Son of God."</verse>
        <verse number="64">"Yes, it is as you say," Jesus replied. "But I say to all of you: In the future you will see the Son of Man sitting at the right hand of the Mighty One and coming on the clouds of heaven."</verse>
        <verse number="65">Then the high priest tore his clothes and said, "He has spoken blasphemy! Why do we need any more witnesses? Look, now you have heard the blasphemy.</verse>
        <verse number="66">What do you think?He is worthy of death," they answered.</verse>
        <verse number="67">Then they spit in his face and struck him with their fists. Others slapped him</verse>
        <verse number="68">and said, "Prophesy to us, Christ. Who hit you?"</verse>
        <verse number="69">Now Peter was sitting out in the courtyard, and a servant girl came to him. "You also were with Jesus of Galilee," she said.</verse>
        <verse number="70">But he denied it before them all. "I don't know what you're talking about," he said.</verse>
        <verse number="71">Then he went out to the gateway, where another girl saw him and said to the people there, "This fellow was with Jesus of Nazareth."</verse>
        <verse number="72">He denied it again, with an oath: "I don't know the man!"</verse>
        <verse number="73">After a little while, those standing there went up to Peter and said, "Surely you are one of them, for your accent gives you away."</verse>
        <verse number="74">Then he began to call down curses on himself and he swore to them, "I don't know the man!"</verse>
        <verse number="75">Immediately a rooster crowed. Then Peter remembered the word Jesus had spoken: "Before the rooster crows, you will disown me three times." And he went outside and wept bitterly.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter number="27">
        <verse number="1">Early in the morning, all the chief priests and the elders of the people came to the decision to put Jesus to death.</verse>
        <verse number="2">They bound him, led him away and handed him over to Pilate, the governor.</verse>
        <verse number="3">When Judas, who had betrayed him, saw that Jesus was condemned, he was seized with remorse and returned the thirty silver coins to the chief priests and the elders.</verse>
        <verse number="4">"I have sinned," he said, "for I have betrayed innocent blood.What is that to us?" they replied. "That's your responsibility."</verse>
        <verse number="5">So Judas threw the money into the temple and left. Then he went away and hanged himself.</verse>
        <verse number="6">The chief priests picked up the coins and said, "It is against the law to put this into the treasury, since it is blood money."</verse>
        <verse number="7">So they decided to use the money to buy the potter's field as a burial place for foreigners.</verse>
        <verse number="8">That is why it has been called the Field of Blood to this day.</verse>
        <verse number="9">Then what was spoken by Jeremiah the prophet was fulfilled: "They took the thirty silver coins, the price set on him by the people of Israel,</verse>
        <verse number="10">and they used them to buy the potter's field, as the Lord commanded me."</verse>
        <verse number="11">Meanwhile Jesus stood before the governor, and the governor asked him, "Are you the king of the Jews?Yes, it is as you say," Jesus replied.</verse>
        <verse number="12">When he was accused by the chief priests and the elders, he gave no answer.</verse>
        <verse number="13">Then Pilate asked him, "Don't you hear the testimony they are bringing against you?"</verse>
        <verse number="14">But Jesus made no reply, not even to a single charge--to the great amazement of the governor.</verse>
        <verse number="15">Now it was the governor's custom at the Feast to release a prisoner chosen by the crowd.</verse>
        <verse number="16">At that time they had a notorious prisoner, called Barabbas.</verse>
        <verse number="17">So when the crowd had gathered, Pilate asked them, "Which one do you want me to release to you: Barabbas, or Jesus who is called Christ?"</verse>
        <verse number="18">For he knew it was out of envy that they had handed Jesus over to him.</verse>
        <verse number="19">While Pilate was sitting on the judge's seat, his wife sent him this message: "Don't have anything to do with that innocent man, for I have suffered a great deal today in a dream because of him."</verse>
        <verse number="20">But the chief priests and the elders persuaded the crowd to ask for Barabbas and to have Jesus executed.</verse>
        <verse number="21">"Which of the two do you want me to release to you?" asked the governor. "Barabbas," they answered.</verse>
        <verse number="22">"What shall I do, then, with Jesus who is called Christ?" Pilate asked. They all answered, "Crucify him!"</verse>
        <verse number="23">"Why? What crime has he committed?" asked Pilate. But they shouted all the louder, "Crucify him!"</verse>
        <verse number="24">When Pilate saw that he was getting nowhere, but that instead an uproar was starting, he took water and washed his hands in front of the crowd. "I am innocent of this man's blood," he said. "It is your responsibility!"</verse>
        <verse number="25">All the people answered, "Let his blood be on us and on our children!"</verse>
        <verse number="26">Then he released Barabbas to them. But he had Jesus flogged, and handed him over to be crucified.</verse>
        <verse number="27">Then the governor's soldiers took Jesus into the Praetorium and gathered the whole company of soldiers around him.</verse>
        <verse number="28">They stripped him and put a scarlet robe on him,</verse>
        <verse number="29">and then twisted together a crown of thorns and set it on his head. They put a staff in his right hand and knelt in front of him and mocked him. "Hail, king of the Jews!" they said.</verse>
        <verse number="30">They spit on him, and took the staff and struck him on the head again and again.</verse>
        <verse number="31">After they had mocked him, they took off the robe and put his own clothes on him. Then they led him away to crucify him.</verse>
        <verse number="32">As they were going out, they met a man from Cyrene, named Simon, and they forced him to carry the cross.</verse>
        <verse number="33">They came to a place called Golgotha (which means The Place of the Skull).</verse>
        <verse number="34">There they offered Jesus wine to drink, mixed with gall; but after tasting it, he refused to drink it.</verse>
        <verse number="35">When they had crucified him, they divided up his clothes by casting lots.</verse>
        <verse number="36">And sitting down, they kept watch over him there.</verse>
        <verse number="37">Above his head they placed the written charge against him: THIS IS JESUS, THE KING OF THE JEWS.</verse>
        <verse number="38">Two robbers were crucified with him, one on his right and one on his left.</verse>
        <verse number="39">Those who passed by hurled insults at him, shaking their heads</verse>
        <verse number="40">and saying, "You who are going to destroy the temple and build it in three days, save yourself! Come down from the cross, if you are the Son of God!"</verse>
        <verse number="41">In the same way the chief priests, the teachers of the law and the elders mocked him.</verse>
        <verse number="42">"He saved others," they said, "but he can't save himself! He's the King of Israel! Let him come down now from the cross, and we will believe in him.</verse>
        <verse number="43">He trusts in God. Let God rescue him now if he wants him, for he said, 'I am the Son of God.'"</verse>
        <verse number="44">In the same way the robbers who were crucified with him also heaped insults on him.</verse>
        <verse number="45">From the sixth hour until the ninth hour darkness came over all the land.</verse>
        <verse number="46">About the ninth hour Jesus cried out in a loud voice, "Eloi, Eloi, lama sabachthani?"--which means, "My God, my God, why have you forsaken me?"</verse>
        <verse number="47">When some of those standing there heard this, they said, "He's calling Elijah."</verse>
        <verse number="48">Immediately one of them ran and got a sponge. He filled it with wine vinegar, put it on a stick, and offered it to Jesus to drink.</verse>
        <verse number="49">The rest said, "Now leave him alone. Let's see if Elijah comes to save him."</verse>
        <verse number="50">And when Jesus had cried out again in a loud voice, he gave up his spirit.</verse>
        <verse number="51">At that moment the curtain of the temple was torn in two from top to bottom. The earth shook and the rocks split.</verse>
        <verse number="52">The tombs broke open and the bodies of many holy people who had died were raised to life.</verse>
        <verse number="53">They came out of the tombs, and after Jesus' resurrection they went into the holy city and appeared to many people.</verse>
        <verse number="54">When the centurion and those with him who were guarding Jesus saw the earthquake and all that had happened, they were terrified, and exclaimed, "Surely he was the Son of God!"</verse>
        <verse number="55">Many women were there, watching from a distance. They had followed Jesus from Galilee to care for his needs.</verse>
        <verse number="56">Among them were Mary Magdalene, Mary the mother of James and Joses, and the mother of Zebedee's sons.</verse>
        <verse number="57">As evening approached, there came a rich man from Arimathea, named Joseph, who had himself become a disciple of Jesus.</verse>
        <verse number="58">Going to Pilate, he asked for Jesus' body, and Pilate ordered that it be given to him.</verse>
        <verse number="59">Joseph took the body, wrapped it in a clean linen cloth,</verse>
        <verse number="60">and placed it in his own new tomb that he had cut out of the rock. He rolled a big stone in front of the entrance to the tomb and went away.</verse>
        <verse number="61">Mary Magdalene and the other Mary were sitting there opposite the tomb.</verse>
        <verse number="62">The next day, the one after Preparation Day, the chief priests and the Pharisees went to Pilate.</verse>
        <verse number="63">"Sir," they said, "we remember that while he was still alive that deceiver said, 'After three days I will rise again.'</verse>
        <verse number="64">So give the order for the tomb to be made secure until the third day. Otherwise, his disciples may come and steal the body and tell the people that he has been raised from the dead. This last deception will be worse than the first."</verse>
        <verse number="65">"Take a guard," Pilate answered. "Go, make the tomb as secure as you know how."</verse>
        <verse number="66">So they went and made the tomb secure by putting a seal on the stone and posting the guard.</verse>
      </chapter>
      </book>
  </testament>
</bible>
